<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Politics | Robby Grossman]]></title>
  <link href="http://rob.by/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rob.by/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-20T15:02:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rob.by/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robby Grossman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[robby@freerobby.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['tis the Season]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2008/tis-the-season/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-26T23:53:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2008/tis-the-season</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friends &amp; Family,</p>

<p>I hope you’re all enjoying happy holidays, and I wish you the best of luck in the coming new year.</p>

<p>Rather than leave this as a template holiday note, I thought I would take the moment to bring attention to an important cause that is, unfortunately, very ineffectively lobbied for. This is admittedly a bit long-winded; if you’d like the condensed version, just read the last three paragraphs.</p>

<p>As somebody with several gay friends, the issue of equal rights for homosexuals has struck me more forcefully than I suspect it strikes many straight people. It’s an issue I’ve been forced to confront time and again, if not directly in conversation then indirectly in passing thoughts. Not everybody has a gay friend (though I suspect there are many who do and don’t know it), and I fear that those who don’t wind up examining the issue through the mainstream media’s portrayal of it, rather than through first hand experience and interaction. I hope that this note can speak to everybody, but I’m especially reaching out to the latter category of people.<!--more--></p>

<p>Right now, the obvious thing to talk about is Proposition 8, so let’s recap: groups like “No on 8” were filled with passionate individuals who fought fiercely for their cause. But it didn’t work. The aggressive, sometimes-demonizing attitudes that they showed were ineffective, and the result was a giant step backwards.</p>

<p>Now fast-forward to the aftermath of Proposition 8 and all of the media coverage that has ensued. It’s difficult to find debates on television that don’t erupt into shouting matches. But on the few programs whose arguments aren’t won in decibels, I’ve noticed a common recurrence: many activists (on both sides of the issue) have been comparing and contrasting the matter with the Civil Rights movement. I think that most of these sweeping metaphors are flawed, but there is one–a more subtle one–that I’d like to share:</p>

<p>In 1955, a black woman rode on a bus and refused to give up her seat to a white person who wanted it. She was forcibly removed from the bus, handcuffed and arrested. This woman was <em>not</em> Rosa Parks; it was a single, lower-class 15-year-old named Claudette Colvin, and for reasons that had nothing to do with righteousness or legality, her case never went to court. Edgar Nixon, President of the local NAACP, vetted her after her arrest to find that she’d become pregnant with the illegitimate child of a married man. Politically-in-tune Civil Rights activists like Bayard Rustin knew that the case would be lost in the public eye before it had a shot in court, and Mr. Nixon was persuaded to drop it. Nine months later the married, middle-class, Rosa Parks had her encounter, and Mr. Nixon had his empathetic woman. You know how the story ends.</p>

<p>The lesson here is that while Martin Luther King awed us with powerful and lasting rhetoric (the quote in my mind as I write this is “the arc of the moral universe… bends towards justice”), the truth is that Bayard Rustin’s political instincts were just as important as MLK’s eloquence. Political battles cannot be won apolitically, no matter how righteous the cause. Bayard Rustin understood this and was able to convince other powerful Civil Rights activists of it (including MLK). The Civil Rights movement required not just moral righteousness, but also political cleverness to succeed. Groups like “No on 8” lack the latter as much as they possess the former, and this has impeded their progress tremendously. Having your heart in the right place is not enough, and those who lobby for equal rights now would be wise to learn the lessons from those who did then. The good news is, they’re starting to.</p>

<p>There’s a new group called <a href="http://www.gettoknowmefirst.org">Get to Know Me First</a>. It’s an ad campaign with a more subtle, less divisive, less in-your-face approach to promoting gay rights. Quite simply, it’s an organization of homosexuals asking for voters to get to know who they are before casting judgment. It’s a group that finally preaches to its audience rather than to the choir.</p>

<p>Aggressive politicos seeking swift, quick action may feel that this means is too passive. If you do feel that way, I’d caution you to have a look at history before you settle on your gut reaction. If you want to change legislation with lasting force, you’re going to need to change minds, and minds are changed through inclusion and engagement, not with baseball bats and duct tape.</p>

<p>These guys are the real deal, and if they get funded, I am certain they will have a much more profound impact than the groups that have preceded them. <a href="http://www.gettoknowmefirst.org">GetToKnowMeFirst.org</a> is certified non-profit, so you can deduct any donations that you make to them this year if you do it by December 31. They’ll be getting some of my money, and if you’re feeling charitable in this gift-giving season and believe in their cause, they could certainly use <a href="http://www.gettoknowmefirst.org/donate.html">some of yours</a>, too.</p>

<p>Best wishes and warm regards,
Robby</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where I Was on 9/11.]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2008/where-i-was-on-911/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-11T15:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2008/where-i-was-on-911</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was my junior year of high school. I was in the library when the first plane hit, about to run to Ms. Najman’s classroom for Chemistry or Advanced Physics (she taught both; I don’t know which class it was, my gut recalls the former). We spent the next fifty minutes on her computer trying to find out more, but were blocked by the first and only global internet malfunction of my lifetime. I don’t think we got through to a single news site.</p>

<p>Terrorism was my gut response. The act was inescapably intentional, I thought, but the idea of domestic terrorism to this extreme was so far removed from my day to day life, that such an event would put me in a surreality. But that’s what 9/11 turned out to be. Things were suddenly different. My perception of the world matured more on that day than it did in all of my sixteen years preceding it.<!--more--></p>

<p>9/11 marked my introduction to world affairs. I’d heard of Osama bin Laden, but only in passing. I knew he was Middle Eastern and I knew that he hated our country, and that put me among the more knowledgable students in my class.</p>

<p>The state of politics in America immediately following 9/11 is noteworthy. It’s hard to believe in September, 2008, but seven years ago today, our country was not divided. Democrats and Republicans stood together in an act of unity that was genuine and symbolic. Genuine because both sides knew that an immediate response was necessary and symbolic because nothing makes Americans feel more proud than to see themselves come together for a common purpose. We put faith in each others’ parties. This was lauded by seemingly all Washington pundits, and it extended to the President, too. He had the support of both Republicans and Democrats in Congress. They had little choice. Though we were a 51/49 country, George W. Bush had the 51 and as President he was called upon.</p>

<p>It’s difficult to evaluate exactly how 9/11 altered my personal beliefs because it came at a time when I was politically dizzy. I could have stumbled in any of several directions, but the overwhelming magnitude of 9/11 cast my interests towards terrorism and the Middle East, naturally. I pondered the relative weight of national security in my list of political priorities. Was it too low? I wondered if either party had their heads in the right place, or if we were surely fucked. It was a traumatic time for me, in part because it was my first experience of such human destruction, and in part because I was wholly ignorant with regard to foreign affairs, and thus I had no substantive ideological grounding.</p>

<p>When President Bush announced our invasion of Iraq in 2003, I felt extremely nervous.  I opposed the war knowing that my view didn’t count for anything and that there would be no consequences if I was wrong. I was thankful for that. When people asked me how I felt about it, I replied with ambivalence (not apathy), for fear of being wrong and appearing naive.</p>

<p>My political views have changed little since 2003. I’ve become more firmly grounded in my beliefs. Part of that is because I’ve learned more about the world and how it works since then, and part of it is because I’ve seen what I perceive to be failures of neoconservatism and neorealism. 9/11 was a turning point for me–not because it changed my priorities, but because it forced me to learn about what motivates them and gain a deeper understanding of them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Ted Kennedy]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2008/thoughts-on-ted-kennedy/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-20T16:11:09-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2008/thoughts-on-ted-kennedy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sad, disappointing, heartbreaking. Such adjectives don’t do justice to the Liberal Lion. I have to defer to Michael Long of the National Review, whose story speaks louder than any words I can summon:<!--more--></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A few days after my father died, I received a note from Kennedy’s office — a place I called maybe once a month to swap topics for the radio debate. I was touched, even though Cynical Me knew that it was probably just smart staff work. Still, sending me any acknowledgment at all, given the distant connection, was generous.</p>

  <p>But at the bottom of the note, and in a unique hand, was a small personal line from Kennedy — <em>So sorry, Mike.</em></p>

  <p>I’ve always believed he was, in fact, sorry. Given the man’s life, I can imagine that these things matter to him.</p>

  <p>Call me a sucker if you want. Sure, it was only a few seconds out of his day, and maybe my note was just one more in a stack of births and deaths and Chowder Festival Queens — but those were his seconds and he set them aside for me.</p>

  <p>Not what I expected out of the Liberal Lion who — well, I’m not going to lay it all out again here. If you’re conservative, whatever you’re thinking right now about his politics and his policies and his personal life, I’ve thought the same thing. Still do.</p>

  <p>But it occurred to me that day, and in a very personal way, that there is value — maybe to others, but certainly to the health of my own soul — in separating a man from his mistakes, and of being mindful, even when others are not, that disagreement should not be damnation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can read the entire piece <a href="http://article.nationalreview.com/?q=ODAyM2VmMzA3Y2Y3OWFkYTJjM2E3MzBjOGQ5Y2VhMzQ=">here</a>. I strongly suggest that you do.</p>

<p>I wish you the best, Ted.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Addressing Dissent]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2008/addressing-dissent/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-25T14:11:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2008/addressing-dissent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Upon finding my blog, my Great Uncle Morris voiced disagreement.<!--more--></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Feb. 15, 2008</p>

  <p>Dear Robby,</p>

  <p>I find I disagree with your blog and your messages and since I’m not one to hesitate negative views, even when I suspect they will have no effect, here they are.</p>

  <p>You say I can unsubscribe if I get sick of you and that Hillary fans enter at their own risk. I’ll take the risk, and not telling you what I think would be the easy way out. Unfortunately, unsubscribing would not put an end to the influence that you, and millions like you, seem to be having nation-wide. And far from having no interest in the matter I’m extremely concerned. Of course the worldly consequences of what happens in our elections will be much greater for you than they will be for me. On the practical level, and without being sure, I think that Clinton has a better chance of defeating McCain than Obama.</p>

  <p>What I find deplorable is the dogmatic certitude that you and so many “idealistic” young people–lacking learning, wide reading and world experience–bring to their political activity. Much emotion, high-mindedness and presumed academic credentials, are the prevailing conceits. Most college graduates have hardly begun their educations. I wonder how many of them have read the things Sen. Obama studied at Columbia and Harvard.</p>

  <p>I admit I may not know you well. You once exchanged emails with me when you were in a summer camp. You also communicated when you had some interest in John Barth. But I take it that your more recent years in college veered you to computers and then to an excellent job using them.</p>

  <p>I’m still trying to learn to use my iMac, and I admire computer skills. But such skills are not among the liberal arts, and like chess or mathematics (which I also admire) they are but a tiny part of an adequate education. It’s impressive that you went to Denali. I was once there myself.  But in your early years it might be better to visit places where you encounter people different from yourself, and talk to them, rather than look at landscapes and animals. One other highly selective memory occurs to me. At you parents’ home on one occasion, with a number of people present, you chose to work on Sundokus rather than to converse.</p>

  <p>Some people of your grandparents’ and great grandparents’ generation (I suspect you know little about them) were also very idealistic–and made poor political choices. But they experienced pressures and needs, and studied what they could as much as they could. They were not, as are many members of your generation, involved in what was called “radical chic.”</p>

  <p>I listened to your music on YouTube. It might have been appropriate in your dorm room. (Ditto for your politics.) But why should it be foisted on the world? Simply because you have the digital power to do it? More important, what music do you listen to? What do you read? What the best of the world has to offer to you is better than what the best of you has to offer to the world. It takes time and maturity before this can change.</p>

  <p>I taught through a generation of students who wanted, and felt entitled to, a share in university governance. Later they felt that they should decide what they should read, not their professors. Finally they thought it more important to evaluate their teachers than to be evaluated. Their ignorance of the past became monumental and it included an indifference to the history of their own families.</p>

  <p>Sen. Obama keeps repeating the old saw–you can disagree without being disagreeable. May I suggest that you can agree, and be very polite, and be even more disagreeable. Absent willingness to engage in dialogue, with someone other than the likes of yourself, nothing good will come.</p>

  <p>I have no blog, but you are welcome to attach this open letter to yours.</p>

  <p>Cordially,</p>

  <p>Morris</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is my reply:</p>

<p>Feb 15, 2008</p>

<p>Dear Morris,</p>

<p>I was saddened and disappointed to find that you authored an email that was so filled with unnecessary and unhelpful condescension (suggesting that my politics belong in my dorm room, for example). You should know that I make it a point not to engage in debate with adversaries who take that sort of tone with me; I find such debates to be void of virtuous results. It would be easy for me to respond as if I thought your tone was unintentional, but that would be to condescend to you, and I refuse to do that. As a measure of good faith, I will address your concerns. I respectfully ask that your future correspondence be more substantive and civil.</p>

<p>I think that as a Hillary supporter you should be very careful how you use the word “deplorable.” Bill Clinton, Mark Penn and Howard Wolfson have collectively pegged Obama as all but a lazy, coke-dealing Jesse Jackson. In addition to being ethically void and intellectually dishonest, it’s a very short-sighted move for any Democrat to so alienate the black vote in the way that she has.</p>

<p>I’ve also grown frustrated with the way that Hillary has run on her husband’s name with the good, and separated herself from the bad. If she wants to run on the economic boom of the 90s, that’s fair. But then she also has to live with the criticisms that result from the anti-labor and anti-welfare concessions that her husband made. I do not agree with those decisions and she has not convinced me that she would not make similar concessions. I also profoundly disagree with the notion that Hillary is better-experienced to run the country. In fact, her two most significant political experiences (Hillarycare and the Iraq War Authorization) have proven to be colossal failures. I know from past discussions that we have different stances on the War in Iraq. Mine remains that it never should have happened, and I hold her accountable for her vote to authorize it.</p>

<p>I’ll also add that if you believe my reasons for supporting Obama to be “emotional” as you say, then you are fully uninformed as to the virtues I perceive him to have. I was a fan of Obama before he was a United States senator, and thus long before there was any national movement behind him. I have a friend who worked on his Illinois senate campaign and it was around that time that I familiarized myself with his policies and ideology. His judgment to speak out against the Iraq War from the start has proven sound. Deeper beneath the surface is the fact that as a state senator, he managed to pass legislation that his governor, his police department, his own party, and the Republicans told him was not passable. See this, for example: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/03/AR2008010303303.html">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/03/AR2008010303303.html</a>. I do not believe that Hillary has the tactfulness to pull that off.</p>

<p>Lastly, I’m curious as to your reasons why you think Hillary would be better-suited to beat McCain in the general election; national polling and demographics strongly suggest otherwise. The only thing that separates Clinton from McCain with regard to the War in Iraq is that McCain had the political courage to support the surge early on when it was very unpopular. I think that would hurt Hillary significantly.</p>

<p>Steering away from politics as you did, who are you to tell me what music is good enough for the world to listen to and what music is not? I’m not forcing my music down anybody’s throat; I’m putting it up to be heard by anybody who wants to listen. If you do not, then I suggest you do not. I posted it because I was asked to do so. Elliott Smith’s “Tomorrow Tomorrow” is a work adored by many of his fans. Several of them asked me to perform it and post a video so that they too could learn how to play it (Elliott Smith has deceased and at the time I posted it, no videos of him playing it were known to exist). You may find that it lacks maturity, but the 16,000 people who have seen it, commented on it and rated it 4.5 out of 5 stars on YouTube think otherwise. However “learned” you take yourself to be does not negate that, and it does not hinder the enjoyment that my video has provided to others. I would think somebody as educated as yourself would recognize that, pardon the cliché, the beauty of art is in the eye of the beholder. Do you go through record stores and question the existence of every CD that does not suit your fancy? I’m proud of the music that I post on my web site, and I reject your notion that maturity and age are directly proportional and unavoidably so. I’ve gotten several emails from guitarists–some of whom are approaching your own age–who are still unable to perform the right-hand tremolo-picking technique that I use in the video. There are other folks who would contend that the Jackson 5 produced music worth listening to. Should they have waited until they were your age to release an album? The fact that my age is the only criticism that you could muster about my music vastly increases my confidence about having posted it.</p>

<p>The bands and musicians to whom I listen to most these days are Radiohead, Jon Brion, Elliott Smith, Jeff Buckley and Aimee Mann.</p>

<p>Yours truly,
Robby</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Obama Movement]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2007/the-obama-movement/"/>
    <updated>2007-09-18T22:13:34-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2007/the-obama-movement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Obama Movement</em> is now available for purchase in select bookstores <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Obama-Movement-Barack-Speaks-Americas/dp/0595467032/ref=sr_1_1/102-8060843-4058564?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1190167163&amp;sr=8-1">and on Amazon.com</a>. It features a collection of short essays written by students and young professionals who support Barack Obama in his bid for the United States Presidency. One of those supporters is yours truly.<!--more--></p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2007/the-obama-movement/theobamamovementcover.jpg" alt="The Obama Movement [Book Cover]" /></p>

<p>Check out the press release:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>NEW BOOK EXPLAINS OBAMA’S YOUTH APPEAL</p>

  <p>September 2007:</p>

  <p>A Putnam County native will be published this month in a book that addresses the popularity of Democratic presidential candidate Barack Obama among the youth and young adult crowd. Robby Grossman, age 22, was selected to contribute to The Obama Movement soon after Obama announced his candidacy in February of this year. Created and edited by Joseph Vogel, an author and writing instructor at Brigham Young University, The Obama Movement is a compilation of essays by 25 teens and twentysomethings articulating why they are supporting Barack Obama in his bid for President of the United States.</p>

  <p>The book, which is not an official Obama campaign activity, was inspired by Vogel’s frustration that youth interest in Obama’s candidacy was being misinterpreted as shallow or ephemeral. “The media tends to overlook what’s really going on, what the real story is here?” said Vogel. “Young people are making history. They’re organizing, donating, networking and turning out in unprecedented numbers across the country. They recognize the enormous opportunity we have in front of us.”</p>

  <p>Indeed, not since the Kennedys in the 1960s has a politician so energized the youth of America. The key distinction is that today’s generation is mobilizing through technology and online networking in ways unimaginable to previous campaigns. Hundreds of thousands of previously turned off young people have tuned into the vision of the former community organizer from South Chicago. Online groups have swelled into the hundreds of thousands, creative ads by supporters have dominated YouTube, and interest has translated into record-setting donations and massive turnouts in Iowa and New Hampshire, Nevada and Texas.</p>

  <p>Organizations such as Barack the Youth Vote, founded in early 2007 by Vogel, have built a network of support with the intent of educating peers about Obama, canvassing, registering young voters and encouraging campaign contributions. The Obama for America campaign has embraced the energy and activism of students and young adults to their advantage, organizing Students for Barack Obama and Generation Obama , which now contain over 550 chapters nationwide.</p>

  <p>The Obama Movement contains the personal stories of young people in the trenches of one of the most exciting and significant elections in American history, and reveals why they are determined to make their voices count in 2008.</p>

  <p>Grossman, a 2007 graduate of Wheaton College, currently works as a software engineer in Cambridge, MA. He has worked for numerous county and state campaigns, including the Whitehouse for Senate effort in 2006.</p>

  <p>Vogel, whose book Free Speech 101 was published in 2006, hopes that by giving young people a representative voice in print, he is encouraging all of America to take seriously what its younger generations have to say, beyond the outcome of next year’s elections. “This book is essentially a symbol of a movement,” he said. “Barack Obama has inspired it, but it’s bigger than just him. It’s not his celebrity or his ‘rock-star’ status. It’s his groundup message, his challenge for real citizens participating in a real democracy. It’s about transforming America.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Or <a href="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2007/the-obama-movement/theobamamovementpr.pdf">download it in PDF format</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
