<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Startups | Robby Grossman]]></title>
  <link href="http://rob.by/blog/categories/startups/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rob.by/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-04T16:58:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rob.by/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robby Grossman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[robby@freerobby.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Negotiating Your Startup Job Offer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2013/negotiating-your-startup-job-offer/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T10:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2013/negotiating-your-startup-job-offer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last three years I’ve been on both ends of job offers at startups. One thing that’s struck me is how little most applicants know about what to expect in a job offer, and in many cases, what the written offer they’ve received actually means. I was extremely fortunate that the first startup job offer I received was written by a <a href="https://twitter.com/Pistachio">pair</a> of <a href="https://twitter.com/graysky">founders</a> who had the utmost integrity and explained things very clearly. Since then I’ve learned that not every employee is so lucky.</p>

<p>This post doesn’t aim to teach you negotiation itself, but rather to acclimate you to the standards and vernacular of startup negotiations. It assumes you’re a startup newcomer.<!--more--></p>

<h2 id="salary">Salary</h2>

<p>One of the biggest myths that I’d heard while tucked away in my big company cubicle was that in order to get into the startup game, you had to take a substantial paycut. This is false, especially if you’re a developer in today’s funding climate. VC funded startups pay very close to market rate salaries. Your ask should be the same number it would be at a more established company with hundreds or thousands of people.</p>

<h3 id="seed-stage-companies">Seed-Stage Companies</h3>

<p>An exception to the above statement exists for companies who have raised very little capital and are not generating revenue. These companies do not usually have full salaries budgeted into them. If you join such a seed stage company, you should expect to work for less than a market rate salary until a larger round is raised. However, you should be compensated for this with increased equity.</p>

<p>It’s also a good idea to have a discussion about what your market rate salary will be after raising a Series A. This avoids surprises later. Because you haven’t yet demonstrated your skills inside the company and because the funding timeline is indefinite, it’s difficult for either party to make specific promises. My recommendation is to have something written that states what market rate would be for you right now. This way, if it takes two years to raise a Series A and you’ve grown into a bigger role during that time, you aren’t boxed into a number that you arrived at two years earlier and whose value you’ve surpassed, but you do have a quantitative starting point for determining what your salary will be.</p>

<p>Other methods of compensation and risk adjustment may also arise. For example, when I joined oneforty in 2009, I took a 30% pay cut. We expected to raise money in 6-12 months, and structured my employment offer such that I would receive a 30% bonus upon the raising of a Series A (subject to “outstanding performance” per my manager’s discretion). The offer also stated that at that time, my salary would be raised to a market rate. It did not specify what that market rate would be. Before joining, I informed the founders via email of the other offers I was prepared to pass on, and they told me that what I cited was “in a reasonable range.” The entire process from initial offer to post-Series A adjustment went very smoothly and without any surprises for anyone.</p>

<p>Whatever agreement you come to, make sure you get it in writing. This protects both parties and ensures that everybody leaves the conversation with the same impression. Every lawyer I know attests that there are more fights over what was said than what was written.</p>

<h3 id="what-about-bonuses">What About Bonuses?</h3>

<p>Startups do not typically offer cash bonuses unless they are generating substantial revenues.<sup id="fnref:sales-bonuses"><a href="#fn:sales-bonuses" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> For nonprofitable entities with limited runway, it is much better for everybody that the company provides monthly compensation without accruing variable costs of ~10% of annual payroll every year. It’s easier on the books and it prevents the company from setting expectations that it may be unable to meet. Though your cash compensation will likely be comprised only of salary; you can certainly use a bonus you’d earn elsewhere as leverage during negotiations.</p>

<h2 id="equity">Equity</h2>

<p>Equity procedures and vernacular are by far the least understood component of startup job offers. Especially for employees with no background in business law or finance, the specifics pertaining to equity grants are often wildly misunderstood.</p>

<h3 id="when-equity-goes-wrong-a-narrative">When Equity Goes Wrong: A Narrative</h3>

<p>Four years ago, a company granted you 0.5% of it to join as a seed stage engineer. The company has now raised a Series B, and you’re ready to take your shares and move on.</p>

<p>Not so fast.</p>

<p>First, the company didn’t really grant you 0.5% of it. It granted you the option to <em>buy</em> 0.5% of it at some discount from its seed stage valuation (when you joined). Let’s say that discount was 70% and that valuation was $5M, so you have the option to buy 0.5% ($25k) of it at a 70% discount of $7,500. You decide you’ll just wait until it sells or goes public, then buy your shares for $7,500 and then sell them at market price.</p>

<p>That won’t work either.</p>

<p>Leaving the company invokes your exit clause, which stipulates that you have 90 days to purchase your options, or else you completely forfeit them. The company is not obligated to remind you of this. If you forget to exercise your options during this period, they’re gone. If you don’t have $7,500 to spare during this period, they’re gone. Your only option is to cough up $7,500 or relinquish all of the equity you were told you’d been “given.”</p>

<p>If you’re leaving Facebook, this is a no brainer. But you’re probably not leaving Facebook. You’re probably leaving a B stage company that is growing fast but still has problems with churn or customer acquisition or scalability or some other solvable but imminent problem, and while promising, its success is far from certain. You have to decide whether you want to place a $7,500 wager on this company.</p>

<p>You place the wager, and two years later, the company sells for $20M after a year of mediocre numbers and failing to raise a Series C in a downward-sloping economy. It’s not the beachhouse you were hoping for, but your $7,500 investment looks to be worth $100k based on a 4x multiple of the original $25,000 value, right?</p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>Your stock was common, not preferred. Investors have “preference,” which means they get reimbursed for what they put in before anybody else sees a dime. The company raised $18M in combined seed, Series A and Series B investments. First, those investors get their $18M back. Then, there’s $2M to be distributed proportionally among stakeholders. You’ve come out a narrow 25% ahead because of your discount price ($5M * 0.3 vs 2M). You leave with a $2,500 pre-tax profit on your $7,500 investment.</p>

<p>Nope.</p>

<p>When the company issued new shares to Series A and Series B investors, you got diluted. Your 0.5% of the company now constitutes only 0.35% of it. 0.35% of 2M leaves you with… $7,000.</p>

<p>That’s right. After four years of work and digging into your savings to preserve your stake in the company, you’ve <em>lost</em> $500. You let out a long sigh, lamenting that this “granted” equity became a $500 loss.</p>

<p>This story is contrived, but it is not absurd or unrealistic. I recount it like this to emphasize how important it is for you to understand how equity distribution actually works when you’re negotiating it.</p>

<h3 id="starting-simple-how-does-equity-work">Starting Simple: How Does Equity Work?</h3>

<p>Equity is given in the form of stock options. Stock options are not gifts; rather they are “options” to buy some amount of stock at a fixed, usually discounted price. The nice thing about this system is that, at least in the ideal case, you don’t need to buy the options until you are ready to sell them.</p>

<p>For example, you have options on 1% of a company valued at $1.6M. There are 100k shares outstanding, each worth $16. Your strike price is $0.80, so you make $15,200 before taxes upon selling them:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

\begin{eqnarray*}
\mathbf{Your\ Shares} & = & \mathit{\%\ Ownership} & * & \mathit{Shares\ Outstanding} \\
                     & = & 0.01                  & * & 100,000 \\
                     & = & 1000
\end{eqnarray*}
 %]]&gt;</script>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

\begin{eqnarray*}
\mathbf{Profit} & = & \mathit{Your\ Shares} & * & \mathit{Sell\ Price} & - & \mathit{Your\ Shares} & * & \mathit{Strike\ Price} \\
                & = & 1000            & * & $16                  & - & 1000            & * & $0.80 \\
                & = & $15200
\end{eqnarray*}
 %]]&gt;</script>

<h3 id="how-much-equity-should-i-get">How Much Equity Should I Get?</h3>

<p>There are too many  variables (company stage, company valuation, employee experience, employee domain knowledge, employee salary requirements), let alone disagreement among industry veterans<sup id="fnref:fair-equity"><a href="#fn:fair-equity" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, to generalize how much equity you should get and when, but Babak Nivi put together a <a href="http://venturehacks.com/articles/option-pool-shuffle#market">table of option grants</a> that rings true based on my experiences:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Title Range (%)</p>

  <p>CEO 5 – 10</p>

  <p>COO 2 – 5</p>

  <p>VP  1 – 2</p>

  <p>Independent Board Member  1</p>

  <p>Director  0.4 – 1.25</p>

  <p>Lead Engineer 0.5 – 1</p>

  <p>5+ years experience Engineer  0.33 – 0.66</p>

  <p>Manager or Junior Engineer  0.2 – 0.33</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You’ll notice that Nivi talks about equity in terms of percentages. As Chris Dixon <a href="http://cdixon.org/2009/08/27/the-one-number-you-should-know-about-your-equity-grant">explains</a>, this is the only number you care about in your equity offer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The only thing that matters in terms of your equity when you join a startup is what percent of the company they are giving you. If management tells you the number of shares and not the total shares outstanding so you can’t compute the percent you own – don’t join the company! They are dishonest and are tricking you and will trick you again many times.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s a dangerous game to try to anticipate what your shares will be worth, but if you want to indulge, take your percentage, divide it by two to account for dilution and a low strike price, and multiply it by whatever you think the company might sell for. That’s the ballpark of what a home run hit gets you. Let’s look at a few examples:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
  \mathbf{Equity\ Payout} = \frac{\mathit{Equity\ Percentage} * \mathit{Sale\ Price\ of\ Company}}{2}
</script>

<p>You get 0.5% of a company that sells for $25M: <script type="math/tex">\frac{\mathit{0.005} * \mathit{25000000}}{2}=$62500</script></p>

<p>You get 1% of a company that sells for $15M: <script type="math/tex">\frac{\mathit{0.01} * \mathit{15000000}}{2}=$75000</script></p>

<p>You get 0.25% of a company that sells for $150M: <script type="math/tex">\frac{\mathit{0.0025} * \mathit{150000000}}{2}=$375000</script></p>

<p>Though it’s tempting, if you’re a startup employee, I caution you not to think about equity in such absolute terms, as they are difficult to predict. Look at your equity as a great bonus if things go well. The sad truth is that an overwhelming majority of startups fail, so for the sake of personal financial planning, assume it will amount to nothing. In the best case scenario it will buy you a nice car or provide a down payment on a home. It’s not a ticket to establishing independent wealth or never to work again.</p>

<h3 id="will-i-get-more-equity-after-i-join">Will I get more equity after I join?</h3>

<p>There are a few situations after joining when you may be granted additional equity: first, as new shares are issued, you may be allotted some of them to avoid dilution; second, equity is sometimes used as a performance bonus, especially when companies don’t have enough revenue to provide extra cash; third, equity is often granted as compensation for a promotion.</p>

<h3 id="vesting-schedules">Vesting Schedules</h3>

<p>Your equity should begin accruing as of the start of your employment. Do not listen to any hiring manager who tells you that in order to protect the company, you need to work for a while before you’ll receive any equity.<sup id="fnref:equity-from-day-one"><a href="#fn:equity-from-day-one" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> There is a process called “vesting” that takes care of this and any founder who is both honest and knowledgable uses it.</p>

<p>Vesting lets the company give you some fixed number of stock options, subject to your working at the company for some period of time. Brad Feld <a href="http://www.feld.com/wp/archives/2005/05/term-sheet-vesting.html">explains</a> the standard 4/1 vesting schedule:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Industry standard vesting for early stage companies is a one year cliff and monthly thereafter for a total of 4 years. This means that if you leave before the first year is up, you don’t vest any of your stock. After a year, you have vested 25% (that’s the “cliff”). Then – you begin vesting monthly (or quarterly, or annually) over the remaining period. So – if you have a monthly vest with a one year cliff and you leave the company after 18 months, you’ll have vested 37.25% of your stock.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Vesting is great because it protects everybody. Employees know exactly what they will get if they put in their time, and companies avoid the risk of an employee who takes equity and runs away with it.</p>

<h3 id="trading-salary-for-equity-do-the-math">Trading Salary for Equity: Do the Math</h3>

<p>Some employers talk about equity and salary as dials that you can adjust, increasing one while decreasing the other. Since startups are strapped for cash, this is always presented as the employee giving up some salary in exchange for more equity.</p>

<p>Sometimes these deals are fair, and sometimes they’re not. What makes them difficult and often unfair for the employee is that there are a handful of existential disadvantages that come along with taking equity as a substitute for salary. It’s important that they be understood so that they can be overcome:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Salary accrues over one year, while stock options vest over four years, so in order to break even, the value of your extra stock options needs to be 4x the salary that you’re giving up. In reality it should be even more because your stock is going to be a different class than what the investors get, and that means the investors will get preference over you should the company endure a <a href="http://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/downround.asp#axzz2KbknGfYk">downround</a> or a poor exit. This is immensely unfair to you because if you’re giving up cash for equity, you are effectively investing in the company but not receiving the favorable terms that other investors get.</li>
  <li>Even if the company is doing well, your stock options will likely get diluted at some point over your four year vesting schedule when the company raises more money. This decreases the percentage of the company that you have the right to buy.</li>
  <li>Stock options are a one-time grant, so you’re accepting one-time compensation in exchange for recurring compensation. The portion of your compensation that you receive in equity will not be accounted for in your future salary bumps at the company, and because salary increases are often given in terms of percentages, your losses will likely be compounded during this time.</li>
  <li>Company valuations are monopoly money until their stock becomes liquid. Having $200,000 in stock options doesn’t mean anything if you can’t sell your stock, and you can’t sell your stock unless your company goes public or you find a private buyer in a secondary market, which won’t happen unless your company is far down its path to a successful exit.</li>
  <li>Exercising your stock options has a monetary cost to you. If you get $25,000 in options with a 60% discount, that means the company is chipping in $15,000 for your stock and you’re chipping in $10,000 it.</li>
</ol>

<p>Now that you understand the inherent disadvantages of this trade, you want to know if the specific deal on the table (to exchange some $x in equity for some $y in salary) is a good one. The best way to determine this is to look at the deal that the investors get, and compare it to the deal that you’re getting. You want a risk/reward ratio that is better than theirs.</p>

<p>Let’s start with a losing scenario. Tony Wright <a href="http://www.tonywright.com/2008/a-newbies-guide-to-startup-compensation-or-stock-options-will-make-me-rich">illustrates a typical example</a> where the equity-salary lever is a bad deal for the employee<sup id="fnref:my-claim-not-tonys"><a href="#fn:my-claim-not-tonys" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Let’s say we have an engineer who is getting .5% of the company vested over 4 years. He’s making $80k, but probably could make $90k at a company with limited equity opportunity. Let’s assume a target exit price of $50,000,000 (oh, happy day!).</p>

  <p>Our engineer is spending $10k per year to have a shot at a $62,500 per year. If he spends the full four years there, he’s “invested” $40k for a shot at $250k (a 6x+ return– not bad). When you run the same scenario with a billion dollar exit, it’s starting to look a lot prettier. When you run it at a Flickr-sized exit ($20m), it’s not looking like that great of a bet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A 6x-exit does sound rosy, but when you’re shooting for a big reward, you must also consider the big risk. If you were this employee and you dug into the details here, you’d see that:</p>

<ol>
  <li>You’re taking a bigger risk than the company’s investors are; and</li>
  <li>You receive only half the reward that the company’s investors receive in the case of a success.</li>
</ol>

<p>Let’s say you got into the company when it had a $4M valuation (A $90k engineer receiving a 0.5% equity grant implies (s)he is early). Your 0.5% entitles you to buy $20k worth of its shares at that valuation. That means that after four years, you’ve given up $40k in cash for $20k worth of illiquid stock. If you were an investor in the company, your money would have bought you $40k worth of the stock, it would be preferred stock rather than common stock, and it would not be subject to any vesting period. Dollar for dollar, investors got twice as much stock as you did, and they got it on much better terms.</p>

<p>Now let’s change the hypothetical to show when taking equity might make sense. A Director of Engineering comes on for $110k and 1.25% (he would normally make $140k) after the company raises a Series A and is valued at $14M. He is giving up $120k over four years to pick up $175k worth of options, earning 46% more stock per dollar invested than the investors who put in money at a $14M valuation. This increased reward helps to compensate for the increased risk stemming from the aforementioned disadvantages of taking equity over stock.</p>

<p>If you can afford to play the risk/reward game and want to turn up your equity in exchange for some salary, by all means see if you can find a deal that makes sense. There are founders who offer very meaningful equity grants to employees who are willing to sacrifice a portion of their paycheck. But in my experience, this latter example is the exception and Tony’s example is the rule. Whatever’s on the table, do the math and be cognizant of the tradeoff you’re making.</p>

<h3 id="the-most-important-thing-about-equity">The Most Important Thing About Equity</h3>

<p>Your equity will be worth something or it won’t. Which side of that coin you land on matters more than anything – more than how quickly you vest or how much equity you get or what kind of discount you get or what stage you join at. A bad negotiator at a successful company will wind up with more equity value than a shrewd negotiator at an unsuccessful company.</p>

<p>Betting on equity should imply that you believe in the vision of the company and that you have immense faith in the people you’re working with. At the end of the day, those things will impact how much your equity is worth more than any of the aforementioned advice.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p>With the exception of health insurance, benefits are less numerous and less generous at startups than they are at established companies. Very few startups offer 401k plans; even fewer provide employer matching. The startups I’ve seen or been at that offered 401k plans instituted them because there was some bloc of employees who wanted to put away more than $5k per year ($5k is the maximum you can do on your own via an IRA).</p>

<p>Startups that have raised funding of any sort should provide your health insurance and they should pick up most if not all of the bill. If the startup doesn’t offer a healthcare plan, it should reimburse you for an individual health care plan. The more generous of startups will provide you with dental coverage.</p>

<h2 id="in-conclusion">In Conclusion</h2>

<p>The difficult part of negotiating a startup job offer is learning the inside baseball. If you can get past the jargon that you never saw until today, you’ll find that, like most negotiations, it boils down to math and common sense.</p>

<p>There are plenty of things to adapt to when you switch to startup life – culture, work hours, individual autonomy – but unless you’re committed to joining at the seed stage or earlier, a jarring compensation reduction isn’t one of them.</p>

<p>If you still have questions about something in your offer letter, or if something seems a little fishy, you can ask questions in the comments and I will answer them, or if it’s confidential, you can email me at <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#114;&#111;&#098;&#098;&#121;&#064;&#102;&#114;&#101;&#101;&#114;&#111;&#098;&#098;&#121;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">&#114;&#111;&#098;&#098;&#121;&#064;&#102;&#114;&#101;&#101;&#114;&#111;&#098;&#098;&#121;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;</a> and I’ll respond privately.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="http://graysky.org">Mike Champion</a>, <a href="http://hellohappy.org">Chad Mazzola</a> and <a href="http://pistollake.com">Will Sulinski</a> for reading early drafts of this post and providing valuable feedback.</em></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:sales-bonuses">
      <p>Exceptions exist for roles whose market compensation is typically paid in the form of bonuses, e.g. sales executives who are paid according to how much revenue they bring in.<a href="#fnref:sales-bonuses" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fair-equity">
      <p>I love Joel Spolsky’s <a href="http://answers.onstartups.com/questions/6949/forming-a-new-software-startup-how-do-i-allocate-ownership-fairly/23326#23326">approach to divvying equity</a>, but it is a minority opinion.<a href="#fnref:fair-equity" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:equity-from-day-one">
      <p>Some companies require a board meeting to issue your equity paperwork. This is fine, but the agreement should be retroactive back to your starting date when you receive it.<a href="#fnref:equity-from-day-one" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:my-claim-not-tonys">
      <p>Tony describes only the situation; it is my claim, not his, that the equity tradeoff is a bad one.<a href="#fnref:my-claim-not-tonys" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AWS Risk Mitigation Strategies]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2012/aws-risk-mitigation-strategies/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T10:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2012/aws-risk-mitigation-strategies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even if you’re not ready to roll your own hardware, there’s a lot you can do to minimize your risk of downtime on AWS, and to mitigate the effects when it’s unavoidable.<!-- more --></p>

<h3 id="plan-for-brownouts-following-blackouts">Plan for Brownouts Following Blackouts</h3>

<p>Amazon <a href="http://status.aws.amazon.com/">emphasizes</a> that only “a single availability zone” suffered EC2 and EBS outages, but that is only half the story. The cascading effects that followed are equally important.</p>

<p>For several hours on Friday night, I was unable to bring up a single instance in any of the five US-East availability zones. A commenter correctly <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4182137">pointed out</a> that this is what light utilization reserved instances are for, but in this case that would not have helped. The AWS web console was unreachable, as was the AWS API. I was eventually able to get an “insufficient capacity” error message, at which point a reserved instance may have been helpful, but that was hours later.</p>

<p>I’ve confirmed that others had similar experiences. A source at a company with AWS Platinum Support told me that Amazon was throttling requests and the spawning of new instances in “unaffected” US-East availability zones. It sounds like a barrage of requests came in to launch new EC2 instances in these other availability zones, and Amazon was unable to support the demand.</p>

<p>At <a href="http://shareaholic.com">Shareaholic</a> we determined a long time ago that implementing full redundancy was not worth the engineering cost. However, that was based on the assumption that if one availability zone went offline, we could bring up new instances in another one immediately to keep our core services operating. This proved to be a flawed assumption. We did not anticipate that the loss of one availability zone would create more demand than Amazon could handle in the other four.</p>

<h3 id="use-automated-infrastructure-to-save-time-and-headaches">Use Automated Infrastructure to Save Time and Headaches</h3>

<p>Without exception, what saves me the most time recovering from an AWS outage is that our infrastructure stack is automated with Chef. Deploying new code or provisioning a new server requires only one terminal command.</p>

<p>Automated infrastructure also provides an additional benefit: it serves as documentation for the configuration of every server. Not sure what your haproxy.cfg should look like? It’s in Chef. Not sure how to setup your MySQL slave? It’s in Chef.</p>

<p>Whether you use Chef, Puppet, Rubber or homegrown deploy scripts, having an automated infrastructure stack saves you time and ensures that you aren’t struggling to piece together a working config file at a critical moment.</p>

<h3 id="use-low-ttl-values-for-faster-dns-updates">Use Low TTL Values for Faster DNS Updates</h3>

<p>At Shareaholic, we set a very low DNS TTL value (300 seconds) on our top level domain so that we can push out DNS updates within five minutes. Unfortunately, this is not 100% reliable: some ISPs do not enforce these low TTL values because they require more frequent fetching. Users of such ISPs resultantly see longer downtime than everybody else. Users whose ISPs react properly receive correct IP addresses within five minutes from when we push an update.</p>

<p>This, combined with our use of Chef, is our best shot at restoring downed services in minutes rather than hours.</p>

<h3 id="use-virtualized-hardware-not-services-to-reduce-risk-of-outages">Use Virtualized Hardware, Not Services, to Reduce Risk of Outages</h3>

<p>Amazon Web Services can be used either to virtualize raw hardware (EC2 instances with instance storage) or to virtualize core web services (ELB, EBS, RDS, etc.). This weekend’s ELB, EBS and RDS failures demonstrate that you are at much greater risk of a service disruption if you use the latter. None of our instance storage EC2 instances suffered outages.</p>

<p>For this reason, at Shareaholic, we’ve avoided using AWS’ proprietary services whenever possible. Instead of using ELB, we run our own <a href="http://haproxy.1wt.eu/">HAProxy</a> load balancers. This has reliably fixed the problem of visitors getting directed to unresponsive instances when they go down. Unfortunately, it also means that we own the burden of implementing redundant load balancers. We got burned when the AWS API timed out, prohibiting us from reassigning our Elastic IP addresses to our redundant machines. However, we were still able to get our home-grown load balancers back up hours before Amazon resolved its ELB failures.</p>

<p>We’ve rolled our own MySQL, Redis, MongoDB and Riak for the same reason. We still suffered downtime because we rely on EBS (which is something we’ll work to avoid in the future), but our recovery efforts were made easier and more timely by the fact that we manage our data and load balancing stacks in-house.</p>

<h3 id="determine-in-advance-what-risks-youre-willing-to-take">Determine in Advance What Risks You’re Willing to Take</h3>

<p>My post-downtime debrief boils down to one question:</p>

<p><em>Knowing what we know now, what engineering work would have been worth doing in advance to mitigate the downtime we just had?</em></p>

<p>Usually my answer to this question is “none.” This varies by business, but a few hours to a day of downtime per year is often less expensive than the engineering required to avoid it.</p>

<h3 id="in-conclusion">In Conclusion</h3>

<p>Amazon Web Services is not one big service that stays up or goes down. It is comprised of many services of varying complexity. By understanding their individual reliabilities, organizations can engineer around many of AWS’ shortcomings.</p>

<p>Still, there’s no silver bullet. When things do go wrong, the responsibility of recovery falls on you, the AWS customer. By determining in advance what risks you’re willing to take, preparing your DNS for faster updates and automating the generation of your infrastructure, you can respond more quickly when you need to.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="http://graysky.org">Mike Champion</a> and <a href="http://nirvdrum.com">Kevin Menard</a> for proofreading this post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Responding to Criticism]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2011/responding-to-criticism/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T10:00:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2011/responding-to-criticism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2006 I participated in <a href="http://www.nols.edu/courses/locations/alaska/aksemester.shtml">NOLS’ Summer Semester in Alaska</a>, a 75-day kayaking, backpacking and mountaineering course, which helps students gain wilderness and leadership skills.</p>

<p>A few days in I got my first review. I was a wreck. I packed my backpack as if I were paying homage to the Leaning Tower of Pisa. The most palatable meals I cooked were the ones that were burned beyond recognition. I might have been able to properly affix a rainfly to a tent, but I’ll never know because nobody trusted me to keep their tent dry. You know that guy who played on your middle school basketball team who had great hustle and personality but couldn’t make a layup? The guy the coach wanted to do well, but would never take chances with in the 4th quarter? That was me at the start of my first NOLS course.<!--more--></p>

<p>My second review provided a laundry list as long as the first one. “Is there <em>anything</em> I’m doing right?”, I fished. The instructor looked me squarely in the eyes and told me that I’m accepting and responding to their criticisms very well - certainly better than anybody else on the trip, and maybe better than any other student he’s had. If I were young and stupid, I’d have thought this was the most condescending thing he could possibly say to me. Oh wait, I was young and stupid, and that’s exactly what I thought. Miraculously aware that acting somber or exploding would be of no value, I swallowed and said “thanks.”</p>

<p>I later came to understand that my instructor had actually paid me one of the most gracious compliments I’d ever receive. Over the next week, my skills improved – not hugely, but demonstrably. I continued receiving feedback and making iterative progress over the duration of the course, and it eventually became clear to me, and to others, that I had more than paid off my skills deficit.</p>

<p>The reason I was so offended at first is that I thought that taking criticism was the standard of a student in a student-teacher relationship. To me it was like force-praising a bad teacher by saying “you do a great job showing up to class everyday.” <em>That’s what you’d say to a teacher who had no teaching skills.</em> But I quickly learned that my analogy was flawed. Taking criticism was a skill in itself. There were students who did not take feedback well. To this day I feel very sorry for them, because they lost out on 75 days worth of fantastic wilderness lessons.</p>

<p>And here’s why: nobody was willing to criticize these people after the first week because everybody knew it would lead to conflict. And so by the mountaineering section, when I was getting advanced critiques on navigating through a whiteout (very, very difficult), the more defensive folks were just trotting along, with the same navigation skillsets they had when they started.</p>

<p>Eventually I returned to civilization, and a while later I got my first job. I learned that people function exactly the same way in the office. I’ve seen people at work who take criticism well and respond with a thank you. They continue to get constructive feedback because people feel safe giving it to them. I’ve also seen people who explode in the way that I miraculously avoided despite being young and stupid. I feel sad when I see people do this, because I know that when everybody else is learning the advanced techniques for navigating their corporate worlds (very, very difficult), these people will be trotting along, the same as they were when they started.</p>

<p>Do everything you can to be in that first group of people. No matter how harsh or personal or crushing someone’s feedback feels, take it constructively and with the best of intentions. Show them gratitude for having the courage to help you in a way that was probably uncomfortable for them. If you don’t respond positively, they’ll never be honest with you again and you’ll miss out on a lot of invaluable learning opportunities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing for People, Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2011/writing-for-people-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-18T00:03:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2011/writing-for-people-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year I <a href="/2010/writing-for-people">wrote</a> about the importance of writing for people rather than search engines, two target audiences that often compete with each other on the web.</p>

<p>A similar problem occurs when authors write for companies instead of people. I see this most at business-to-business companies, where the customer is another company rather than a human. It’s important to remember that it’s always a human who will be reading your copy.<!--more--></p>

<p>One way to make that easier is to imagine the people who are reading your copy. Conjuring that image forces you to speak to them on their terms. I think a leading cause of corporate nonsense speak is the  failure of copywriters to personify the audience they’re talking to.</p>

<p>For the benefit of my <a href="http://www.extension.harvard.edu/courses/spch.jsp#e-130">Executive Speaking</a> classmates, many of whom work at big business-to-business companies, I decided to make my final semester speech on this topic.</p>

<p>The slides contain several examples, citing both successes and failures. You can <a href="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2011/writing-for-people-part-2/Writing-for-People.pdf">download them</a> or view them below.</p>

<div style="width:595px" id="__ss_7659704"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/7659704" width="595" height="497" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<h2 id="credits">Credits</h2>

<p>A few of my examples came from UX Designer <a href="http://www.natashascorner.com/">Natasha Lloyd</a>. Specific citations are at the bottom of each applicable slide.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leadership]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.by/2011/leadership/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-10T10:29:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.by/2011/leadership</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Leaders show themselves in various forms. There are rhetorical magicians (Barack Obama) and iconic revolutionaries (Steve Jobs). There are also workplace leaders - the silver-tongued employee who can articulate issues several steps beyond what others are thinking, or the clever, diligent coworker whose performance alone encourages others.</p>

<p>Whatever the kind, leaders have three priceless skills: they’re doers, they persuade, and they inspire.<!--more--></p>

<h2 id="be-a-doer">Be a Doer</h2>

<p>This is widely accepted as an absolute necessity in startup circles, so I’ll leave it at that and let you read <a href="http://37signals.com/rework/">37signals’ take on it</a> if you want an explanation (see chapter: “Everybody Works”).</p>

<h2 id="persuasion">Persuasion</h2>

<p>To persuade is to find common ground among your audience, anchor into it, and use it to lead them stepwise through your train of thought, arriving with you at your conclusion or solution. It is a very logically-grounded process, almost entirely syllogistic, but with enough color along the way to keep people interested and motivated to take the next step with you.</p>

<p>At SAP I had the pleasure of working alongside Bob McCarty, an excellent persuasive leader. Sprint planning meetings were often a mess, with total incongruence between business needs and engineering needs. Management wanted more features out of a codebase that wasn’t ready for it, and engineering wanted to take enormous amounts of time to fix things that probably weren’t worth fixing.</p>

<p>Bob, a senior engineer, had a natural knack not only for seeing what was most important for the company, but for walking the rest of us through his thinking in a way that engendered a room full of “oh yeah, yeah!”s. We all knew where we were, but it took a Bob to see where we needed to get to. There was nothing magical about how Bob operated; he just had a lot of foresight and logical consistency, and used those things to build trust and get everybody on the same page. </p>

<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h2>

<p>Inspiration is taking something that seems impossible and making people believe they can accomplish it anyway. This lends itself to metaphor and abstract expression more than persuasion does, but fluffy thinkers are not off the hook: to sell your case, you have to convince your audience that they can really achieve this seemingly impossible task. If you don’t convince them, you’ll come across as naive and be ignored.</p>

<p>The proven way to convince someone that the impossible is possible is to paint them a picture of it and give them something tangible to do. Unlike persuasive leadership, you don’t need to guide them all the way to the solution; you just need to show them what success looks like, and give them an actionable first step that they feel puts them on the correct trajectory.</p>

<p>Obama, for instance, when running for President in 2008, convinced supporters that America could pass health care reform. It didn’t take a cynic to find this daunting. Health care has long been rigged by lobbyists on both sides, and Hillarycare suffered a demoralizing defeat in the mid-90s. These facts were inescapable in the minds of reform supporters, leaving them no reason for optimism.</p>

<p>But Obama was still able to sell it. He painted a picture of what success looked like, by speaking of an America that no longer sends the sick home from hospitals or the disabled into bankruptcy. He pointed to his <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/03/AR2008010303303.html">history</a> of delivering on seemingly impossible legal agendas, and he explained that his bipartisan methods were the first step towards bringing that change to Washington. With that, he gave them a first step - to vote for him.</p>

<h2 id="when-to-use-what">When to Use What</h2>

<p>When should you persuade and when should you inspire? Here’s a good rule of thumb: when a path from a problem to a solution is clear to you, persuade your audience to follow that path. If a solution is unclear, inspire them to find it with you.</p>

<p>Bob was able to map out a full solution to our sprint planning problem in his head and walk us through it. Obama, on the other hand, could not have possibly foreseen the political calculus that would exist two years later, so he opted instead to inspire us to get there with him.</p>

<p>When you’re leading others, consider which approach makes more sense. For an early, idea-stage startup, inspirational leadership will keep people’s minds open and ambitious. On the other hand, if you’ve found your revenue model, it’s probably time to paint the complete picture of what success looks like and explain to your team how they fit into that picture.</p>

<h2 id="credits">Credits</h2>

<p><em>I became aware of most of this while taking Professor <a href="http://www.stevendcohen.net/">Steven D. Cohen</a>’s <a href="http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k65765">public speaking class</a> in 2010. Steven deserves credit for much of what I’ve explained above, and I recommend his class to anybody who wants to become a better leader, speaker or writer.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
