<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reviews | Robby Grossman]]></title>
  <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/reviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-24T23:28:33-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robby Grossman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Impressions of the New iPad]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2012/first-impressions-of-the-new-ipad/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-16T08:53:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2012/first-impressions-of-the-new-ipad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I picked up "the new iPad" this morning. Here are my first impressions:<!--more--></p>

<h2>Look &amp; Feel</h2>

<p>The touchscreen and overall UX is a lot more responsive than my iPad 1 (running iOS 5.1). Apps load substantially faster; I would estimate a 4x speedup. I do not own an iPad 2 so I can't offer a comparison there.</p>

<h2>Screen</h2>

<p>Like I found when upgrading to the iPhone 4, the screen resolution is amazing. The visual difference between icons that are retina display-optimized and the icons that are not is immediately striking.</p>

<p>My only letdown: one of my complaints about my first generation iPad is that the blacks are a bit bright. This is especially noticeable when watching movies. I was hoping that the increased color saturation on the new iPad's retina display would address this and keep them darker, but after comparing Netflix playback on both of them, I do not see any difference.</p>

<h2>Dictation</h2>

<p>The dictation function is very fast. I dictated eight sentences in one take and the iPad had them transcribed in under a second - about as fast as Apple makes Siri look in its commercials. Textual accuracy was near-perfect (it mistook "is" for "in" and "the" for "a"), and could definitely be used for publishing longer form text on the go after a quick proofread.</p>

<h2>Data Plan</h2>

<p>I have a grandfathered AT&amp;T unlimited data plan from my original iPad. I searched around and called AT&amp;T to verify I could move it to the new one. They assured me I could, and I'm happy to report that transferring it to the new device was fast and straightforward. There were no gotchas or tricks intended to get me to cancel it. My existing plan was selected by default:</p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2012/first-impressions-of-the-new-ipad/unlimited-data.jpg" alt="Unlimited data plan selected by default" /></p>

<p>Update:
Thanks to @kevinebaugh for <a href="https://twitter.com/kevinebaugh/status/180654166681718784">pointing out</a> that I initially used the dictation feature incorrectly. I've updated the review to reflect how it works when used properly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GarageBand Has Found Its Interface]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-16T00:29:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is what you can do with GarageBand for iPad in about 2 hours:</p>

<p><video width='' height='' preload='none' controls poster=''><source src='http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/music/garage-band-jam.m4a' type='video/mp4; codecs="avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2"'/></video><!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/music/garage-band-jam.m4a">Download link</a></p>

<p>I wrote this song for the purpose of trying GarageBand for iPad this evening. I used vocals, guitars and virtual instruments in ways that I believe most people would use them, and I capped the project at two hours.</p>

<h2>Composition</h2>

<p>The above song was recorded entirely on a <strong>first generation iPad</strong>. It consists of eight virtual tracks: two recorded acoustic guitars, two recorded vocal tracks, two recorded electric guitars, a virtual bass, and a virtual drumkit. All audio tracks were recorded with the iPad's internal condenser microphone.</p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface/Final_Track_Layout.png" alt="Final Track Layout" /></p>

<h2>Recording Process</h2>

<p>The two acoustic guitar tracks are panned about 75% left and 75% right. The left is strumming chords; the right is alternating between chords and arpeggiated notes. I chose the "small room" preset for both to provide ambiance.</p>

<p>The two vocal tracks are separate takes of the same lines, panned about two thirds left and two thirds right. This process provides a full sound without requiring any unnatural reverb (Elliott Smith is perhaps best known for using this technique; John Lennon and Bon Iver have also employed it).</p>

<p>The two electric guitar tracks are panned about 60% each way. These are not virtual instruments; they are real electric guitars played through a Fender Pro Junior amp. I struggled to maintain a consistent volume because even at 15 watts my Pro Junior was too loud for the iPad's internal mic. I got the levels manageable with a makeshift damper made from tissues.</p>

<p>I created the virtual bass lines by plucking individual strings from chords in the selected key. Non-musicians will appreciate this method because they can improvise without the risk of playing out of key. Musicians, and particularly composers, will find this limiting. There were a couple times when I wanted to create dissonance, and had to change the key in order to pluck an intermediate semitone.</p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface/Virtual_Bass.png" alt="GarageBand Virtual Bass" /></p>

<p>The virtual drumkit is by far the most fun part of creating songs. GarageBand provides two ways to lay down your beats:</p>

<p>The first is a clickable drumset that plays the drum you tap at the time you tap it. Overdubs are allowed within a single track, so you can focus on one drum per take and get the timing right. If you have a specific drumbeat in your head, this is the method you'll need to use to translate it for the virtual drumset. GarageBand lets you quantize virtual instruments (up to the nearest 64th note), so you can stay on rhythm even if your hands aren't perfect.</p>

<p>The other means of entry is a grid onto which you place drums. The grid ranges from simple to complex and from quiet to loud. If you want to experiment with beats or just get a rhythm down to record with (metronomes are boring), this is the quickest way to get up and running. You can also click the die to generate a random beat.</p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface/Virtual_Drums.png" alt="GarageBand Virtual Drums" /></p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<p>GarageBand has found its interface (spoiler: it comes in a 9.7" version, but not 13", 15" or 17"). Buttons that you actually push. Sliders that you actually slide. Drums that you actually hit. Good riddance, mouse; you will not be missed. It feels like this is what the iPad was made to do.</p>

<p>But the impressiveness of the interface is only half of why GarageBand for iPad is so great. The other half is that Apple has proven that the whole of the iPad is greater than the sum of its parts. It isn't that the GarageBand keyboard has better sensitivity and sound than Pianist (though it does), or that the virtual guitar is easier to use than Air Guitar (though it is), or that the beat sequencers are easier to use than Korg's iElectribe (though they are), or that the drums sound better than those of JamPad (though they do), or that the recording interface is smoother than FourTrack's (though it is). It's that all of these things are now integrated perfectly into part of a larger whole. It is an all-in-one-piece music creation suite, and it is the most capable one on the market.</p>

<p>The closest competition it has is the <a href="http://www.bossus.com/gear/productdetails.php?ProductId=818">Boss Micro BR</a>, which trails far behind in several respects. GarageBand is easy and intuitive to use while the Micro BR's functionality is arcane; GarageBand supports eight tracks while the Micro BR supports only four; GarageBand provides several virtual instruments while the Micro BR provides none. The Micro BR is smaller (5.5"x3.25x0.875"), which makes it slightly more portable, but this also contributes to its poor usability. My Micro BR has served me well for years. Tomorrow it goes up on Craigslist.</p>

<p><img src="http://robby-blog.s3.amazonaws.com/2011/garageband-has-found-its-interface/micro-br.jpg" alt="Boss Micro BR" /></p>

<h2>Room for Improvement</h2>

<p>I'd like to see an input level adjustment in the next version. Controlling individual track volumes at playback time is not sufficient for this purpose, especially for songs that vary from quiet vocals to loud, distorted guitars.</p>

<p>A more traditional drum machine interface (with individual tracks for each drum laid out on a timeline) would be helpful for creating drumbeats that exist in my head. The touch sensitivity of the on-screen drumset is impressive but imperfect. It's frustrating to get through 14 out of 16 measures and then miss a beat.</p>

<p>The condenser mic in my iPad (again, first generation) is acceptable, but leaves something to be desired, particularly on the high end. I don't know if this mic has been upgraded in the iPad2, but something of higher quality would be much appreciated. In the mean the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blue-Microphones-Yeti-USB-Microphone/dp/B002VA464S/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1300250784&amp;sr=8-1">Blue Yeti</a> is an excellent USB microphone, and works with the <a href="http://store.apple.com/us/product/MC531ZM/A">camera connection kit</a>. Obviously, this makes the setup much less portable.</p>

<h2>A Note on iPad vs iPad 2 Performance</h2>

<p>GarageBand's performance on my first generation iPad was noticeably but not painfully sluggish. The most frequent lag occurs when switching between the track and recording screens. It lasts for about one second.</p>

<p>There is another lag, longer in duration but less frequent in occurrence, that I ran into seemingly arbitrarily. A box will pop up that says "Optimizing Performance" and you will have to wait 15-20 seconds while it chugs along. I encountered this four or five times over the course of two hours. I suspect what GarageBand is doing is loading audio content into and out of RAM. If that's the case, then performance should be better on the iPad 2, which has 512MB as opposed to the 256MB of the original.</p>

<h2>TL;DR</h2>

<p>GarageBand for iPad is the most complete and capable all-in-one music creation package available anywhere. It's fun, it's easy, and it's effective. At $4.99, it has replaced my $220 Micro BR.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Kinesis Advantage Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2010/review-kinesis-advantage-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-06T09:00:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2010/review-kinesis-advantage-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently replaced my work and home keyboards with the <a href="http://www.kinesis-ergo.com/advantage.htm">Kinesis Advantage</a>. These are my collected thoughts on it after two full months of daily use.<!--more--></p>

<h2>Adjustment Period</h2>

<p>Adjusting to the Kinesis Advantage layout took some time. It is not a typical ergonomic keyboard, and the differences are more than the separated hand positions. It spaces and aligns the keys differently. Many non-alphanumeric keys have different positions. Even if you have perfect typing habits, you will suffer during the break-in period.</p>

<p>The good news is that the pain ends quickly. For alphanumeric keys, I was back to my normal speed within a week. For special keys (chiefly command, option, control, tilda, backspace) it took me two to three weeks to reach full speed. The arrow keys were particularly difficult to adjust to; they required a full month.</p>

<h2>Comfort</h2>

<p>My previous keyboard was a standard Apple chiclet model. I've always had minor wrist discomfort, but the Apple Keyboard brought out the worst of it. It became unbearable. I had to rest and flex my hands after only 20 minutes of typing. Using a computer had become unsustainable. When I heard about the Kinesis, I read as many detailed reviews as I could find online (not many). I then talked to my friends @zapnap and @nirvdrum, both Kinesis owners, who had nothing but nice things to say about it. I took the plunge.</p>

<p>What a world of difference. Two months later <strong>my wrist pain is gone</strong>. Not only does it feel better when I type, but also when I play guitar and piano. There were certain discomforts that I had grown accustom to over the years, which I had accepted as common or inevitable. Yet after just two months with the Kinesis they are gone. I began feeling relief within a couple of days. My wrists gradually felt better for a little over a month until the pain was entirely gone. In hindsight I cannot believe I waited so long to do something about it.</p>

<h2>Typing Speed</h2>

<p>My typing speed has also benefited. Part of this is because my hands are more relaxed and I can hit the keys faster, but mostly it's because my hands don't travel as far for routine tasks. I don't have to move my right hand to use arrow keys; I no longer have to place my pinky, middle finger and thumb into an awkward position to hit control+command+3; I no longer need my pinky to press backspace (overuse of the pinky stresses tendons, which can lead to wrist pain). <strong>The Kinesis layout, once I became used to it, proved much more efficient than a traditional qwerty layout</strong>.</p>

<h2>Macros</h2>

<p>The Kinesis takes an optional footswich ($35), which I highly recommend. It allows you to activate the number pad in a hands-free manner. It also gives you quick access to your custom macros.</p>

<p>I did not expect to use macros, but they have proven very useful for inputting certain keyboard shortcuts. For instance, I have an app called MercuryMover that moves windows to preset locations. It is activated by pressing control+command+up. This is awkward and difficult to remember. Instead, I have a custom mapping to footswitch+w, which triggers that series of keys.</p>

<h2>Quirks</h2>

<p>There are a few things about the keyboard that I would change if I had the chance:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>It's loud. Clickety-clack is unavoidable when using it.</p></li>
<li><p>Macros cannot be listed, backed up or restored. If you overwrite them, they're gone. If you forget one, there's no means to recall it.</p></li>
<li><p>There are no finger placement indentations on the "f" and "j" keys. The Kinesis has a unique feel to it that in my opinion renders these unnecessary, but I missed them until I fully adjusted.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Answers to Anticipated Questions</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Dvorak legends are available.</p></li>
<li><p>If you don't like the default layout, you can map any key to any other key.</p></li>
<li><p>Look for <a href="http://208.84.117.151/Merchant2/merchant.mvc?Screen=CTGY&amp;Category_Code=CKBDUSB%28R%29">refurbs</a>! I saved $60 per keyboard by choosing this option. It looks brand new and carries the full warranty.</p></li>
<li><p>In my opinion the Pro model is not worth the cost difference. The memory provided for macros on the standard model is plenty.</p></li>
<li><p>The foam wrist pads (included) are a nice touch. They are definitely more comfortable than the bare plastic.</p></li>
<li><p>I have no issues switching between a Kinesis and a traditional keyboard. I routinely use my MacBook's built-in keyboard when I travel.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>If you're considering buying a Kinesis, feel free to ask questions in the comments of this post and I will respond to them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on the Kindle]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2009/thoughts-on-the-kindle/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-24T12:25:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2009/thoughts-on-the-kindle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A week ago I purchased an Amazon Kindle. These are my initial impressions. I am using the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0015T963C">6" Kindle</a> with the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?ie=UTF8&amp;nodeId=200324680">free 2.3 firmware update</a>.<!--more--></p>

<h2>It's easy to use.</h2>

<p>Your father and your grandmother can use the Kindle. They may need your help creating an account and entering a credit card number the first time, or linking it to their Amazon account if they have one. After that it is as simple as browsing the store and selecting "Buy" when they find what they want to read. There are no passwords to remember. There are no credit card security codes to enter. You find the book you want -- either by searching or by browsing -- and then you select "Buy."</p>

<h2>The device is transparent.</h2>

<p>I really like technology. Whether it's my MacBook or my iPhone or my Harmony Remote, I enjoy twiddling with gadgets. But I don't want my reading experience to feel technology-driven. Accordingly, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0015T963C">this claim</a> by Amazon caught my eye:</p>

<blockquote><p>The most elegant feature of a physical book is that it disappears while you're reading. Immersed in the author's world and ideas, you don't notice a book's glue, the stitching, or ink. Our top design objective was to make Kindle disappear—just like a physical book—so you can get lost in your reading, not the technology.</p></blockquote>

<p>This they pulled off very well. Reading on the Kindle is very natural. It does not feel techy, and it does not feel like a gadget. It will not feel quaint the next time you pick up a paperback.</p>

<h2>PDFs render well.</h2>

<p>I held off on the Kindle until it was able to display the PDF eBooks I've purchased over the years. It renders them very well. If things appear too small, you have the option of using landscape mode to zoom in on the pages. One caveat: if you have a PDF that makes use of color, it will display on the Kindle as grayscale and may be harder to read.</p>

<h2>The dictionary is convenient.</h2>

<p>Looking up a word on the Kindle is as simple as putting the cursor next to it. Do this and you'll see the definition at the bottom of the screen. It is seamless and much less interruptive than having to break out a dictionary.</p>

<h2>DRM is scary.</h2>

<p>The Kindle uses <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_rights_management">Digital Rights Management</a>, which prevents buyers from having full control over the electronic goods that they purchase. Examples of DRM include MacroVision, which prevented VHS tapes from being copied, and UOP, the protocol that can stop you from fast forwarding through previews on DVDs. DRM is at best inconvenient and at worst paralyzing.</p>

<p><strong>It's inconvenient when</strong> my girlfriend wants to read a book that I have purchased. I cannot transfer the book to her Kindle; the only option is to let her borrow my device.* This is not a good solution for either of us, and in this case a hard copy of a book is more convenient and more functional than a Kindle copy.</p>

<p><strong>It's paralyzing if</strong> the Kindle fails. If the Nook or any other device wins the ebook game single-handedly, you will lose every book you have purchased. Eventually your hardware will malfunction. You will not be able to replace it, and you will not be able to read your Kindle books on any other device. This is because Amazon's DRM prevents you from viewing your Kindle books on unauthorized devices. I don't think this is likely, but it is possible.</p>

<p>When I buy a paper book, I consider myself  the "owner" of that book. I can do whatever I want with it. This is not the case when I buy a Kindle book. The Kindle's use of DRM means that when I purchase a Kindle book, I am merely a "user" of it. Amazon retains full control over it. With DRM, Amazon can prevent me from being able to read my books at any time and for any reason. The <a href="http://pogue.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/07/17/some-e-books-are-more-equal-than-others/">1984 Fiasco</a> exemplifies this. That would not have been possible without DRM.</p>

<h2>Sometimes Kindle books cost more.</h2>

<p>There are occasional <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Theres-Thing-Public-Speaking-OneConversation/dp/B002PJ4GTK/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1260157299&amp;sr=1-1">examples</a> where a mass market paperback is cheaper than a Kindle version. It is frustrating when I have to pay more for a medium whose cost of goods sold is effectively zero. In Amazon's defense, this is the exception and not the rule. Still, I think Amazon should be sure they are <em>never</em> charging more for the electronic copy than they are for the paperback equivalent.</p>

<p>Additionally, if I purchase a hard copy of a book from Amazon, the Kindle edition should be either free or highly discounted. At minimum I should be able to purchase a cheaper bundle of both versions. The progressive publishers like O'Reilly already do this. Amazon does not.</p>

<h2>Academia has not been penetrated.</h2>

<p>As a student, the Kindle would be of much greater benefit to me if I could use it for my coursework. Sadly, none of the textbooks I need are available in Kindle versions.</p>

<ul>
<li>A <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=kindle+DRM+python+scripts">google search</a> reveals that some clever folks have found a way around this. However, removing DRM without permission from the publisher is a violation of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Millennium_Copyright_Act">Digital Millennium Copyright Act</a>, and I'm assuming that most people won't want to resort to that.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Gig: a Self-Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2006/my-first-gig-a-self-review/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-06T03:13:28-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob-by.herokuapp.com/2006/my-first-gig-a-self-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Wednesday night at 8:30pm, I opened for Jake Armerding at the <em>Lyon's Den</em>, Wheaton College's student-run coffeehouse. It was my first public performance that wasn't an open mic. And it felt like it.</p>

<p>I first realized how nervous I was when I picked up my water and took a sip. I wasn't trying to quench my thirst; I was trying to put off performing. I was doing everything I could think of to buy time.  Sip. Cough. Oops I lost my pick.  Check the mic levels. Again. Eventually I had to start.<!--more--></p>

<p>And I did--with a cover of Elliott Smith's <em>Condor Ave</em>. I sang the second verse well, but also twice. My nervousness had manifested itself through forgetfulness, and there I was singing an unintentional reprise. At first I wasn't sure if anyone would notice, but when I looked at my friend Ryan and saw the smirk on his face, I chuckled, and then so too did the girl on the couch in front of me. Because hey, it's kind of funny.</p>

<p>My original <em>So Susie Stopped Sleeping</em> came second. Of my two original and complete songs, this is the one of which I'm more proud. Aside from some vocal shakiness, I was satisfied with how I performed this song.</p>

<p>Next came my other original, which currently lacks a title. For now I'll call it <em>The Song I Should've Left Out</em>. My voice wobbled like it was walking across a tightrope, trembling so fast that my intro falsetto sounded more like a failed vibrato. Quantum physacists claim that the observation of something changes it. I see what they mean.</p>

<p>My fourth and final song was another Elliott Smith cover: <em>Tomorrow, Tomorrow</em>. This is the song of which I'm most proud to be able to play. I think it's because I once saw Elliott play it, told myself I'd never be able to do so, and then wound up nailing it two weeks later. The crowd would never know that, however, because I did anything but nail it on Wednesday night.</p>

<p>In my own defense, it's very difficult to do tremolo when your hands are so tense that your fingers are cramping. When I noticed this occurrance, I wondered what I could do to correct it. That's when the other things went wrong. I missed the opening vocal line and blew the first verse riff. Then the bridge came. "Thank God I made it," I thought. I should've been thinking about how the bridge went, because apparantly I'd forgotten. After an awkward pause and an off-beat chord change I stumbled my way through the last verse and played the three-chord outro.</p>

<p>I told people to stick around for Jake's set and walked off the stage. At this point I'd learned my first lesson: playing for yourself and playing for others are two distinct things. At least for me, at least for now.</p>

<p>The next lesson I got was that a friendly crowd is going to give friendly feedback, regardless of whether or not it's warranted. "You did great!" and "You were awesome!" are only meaningful remarks if there's a chance that they won't be made. When your girlfriend and your buddies are present, there's no such chance. I knew this going in, and frankly I would've felt better and more at ease if I knew nobody in the room, but there's really no kind way to ask your friends to leave.</p>

<p>Though not immediately recognizable, there were highlights. For starters, Jake was really good to me. He asked people to cheer for me again after he played his opener, and he later remarked that he himself didn't know any of the chords I was playing. At times I wasn't sure that I did either, but I could at least take pride in reaching outside the domain of major and minor chords--something I try hard to do. His bassist, Richard Gates later told me that he liked <em>So Susie Stopped Sleeping</em>. This too was meaningful to me because it was specific. I didn't just "do good!"</p>

<p>I left the <em>Den</em> feeling like I bombed, but I didn't. The truth is that I wanted to kill. I wanted to leave feeling as though I'd impressed everyone who saw me. I wanted to leave people thinking that some day they'd say "I saw Robby Grossman play when he was still a nobody." Anything less would be a failure and unacceptable. That's a pretty high standard for a first gig, I now suppose. It's a good lesson to have learned. I should figure out how to do my thing in front of people before I try to blow them away with it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
